Petr Stepanov

Web designer. Frontend and desktop developer.

stepanovps@gmail.com



(419) 496-86-02



petrstepanov.com



petrstepanov.dribbble.com

Summary

Highly motivated Ph.D. graduate with expertise in computer science, solid state physics and computational technologies. Strong background in building web applications and desktop software. More than five years in user interface and user experience design.

Graduated from BGSU in April 2020. Seeking to either apply for a great software development company, join a startup or continue scientific career. Wishing to become an effective member of a research group as a post-doctorate fellow or find a steady position in the industry. Authorized to work in the US on Optional Practical Training (OPT). Will consider visa sponsorship (H1B) offers.

Skills

Basics. Git, SVN, SSH, HTTP, Linux and terminal usage. VS Code, xCode, Eclipse, NetBeans, Atom. MVC/MVP/MVVM architectural patterns.

UI/UX design. Figma, Sketch, InVision Studio, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, Blender.

Desktop development. Java and Swing, C/C++ and Qt, CERN ROOT, RooFit, Geant4 libraries; compiling from source (gcc, GNU makefiles). Fortran 95.

Frontend and mobile. HTML, CSS (LESS and SASS), Bootstrap, responsive web design, JavaScript and jQuery, npm, gulp, GWT. Some experience with AngularJS, React.js and Backbone.js. WordPress themes development.

iOS development. Swift, UIKit, storyboards.

Backend. Java, Node.js., EJS, PHP

Education

Bowling Green State University

Bowling Green, OH, USA

Aug 2014 → May 2020

PhD in photochemical sciences. Dissertation topic: New developments in positron annihilation spectroscopy techniques—from experimental setups to advanced processing software. View dissertation manuscript.

British Higher School of Art and Design

Moscow, Russia

Dec 2011 → Feb 2012

Intensive: graphical design and visual communications.

National Research Nuclear University

Moscow, Russia

Sept 2004 → Feb 2011

BS and MS in solid state physics. Thesis topic: Defect studies of neutron-irradiated nuclear power plant vessel steels by means of positron annihilation spectroscopy.

Work experience

Research Collaborator Jul 2020 → now

Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab), Newport News, VA USA

Developments in High Energy Physics (HEP). Programming computer simulations of interactions of high energy particles with matter. Statistical analysis of scientific experimental data.

Postdoctoral Researcher Jul 2020 → now

Catholic University of America (CUA), Washington, DC, USA

Developments in deep exclusive and semi-inclusive measurements, in particular those requiring high quality Rosenbluth L/T (longitudinal-transverse) cross section separation. Computer simulations with CERN ROOT and Geant4.

<u>UX and UI</u>. Developing the branding identity and guidelines for companies. Creating logos, establishing visual language and making interactive prototypes (Figma, Sketch, Illustrator). Slicing mockups into responsive HTML and CSS. Preparing image assets for developers. Designing and coding responsive newsletter email templates.

<u>Frontend</u>. Writing gulp build scripts (LESS, SASS, browserify, image compression). Extending Bootstrap and other frameworks to correspond to clients' designs. Writing custom SCSS from scratch. Programming frontend interactions with modular JavaScript and jQuery. Some experience with Node.js, EJS. Participated on projects with Angular and React frameworks.

Mobile. Worked on iOS apps with Swift and UIKit. Familiar with Ionic framework.

Companies. Worked for Otixo, Sweetbridge, Polyient Labs, private investors.

Research Assistant, Software Developer

Aug 2014 → May 2020

Bowling Green State University (BGSU), Bowling Green, OH, USA

Designed and developed a number of desktop GUI software for fitting and interpretation of experimental data: <u>TLIST Processor</u>, <u>SW Calculator</u>, <u>RooPositron</u>. GNU Automake, C++, CERN ROOT and RooFit libraries, Java and Swing.

Created websites for international conferences with registration and payment system workflow (WordPress, PHP, Recurly.js). Designed and programmed the <u>SelimLab</u> research group website (Hexo, Gulp, Bootstrap).

Web Designer, Frontend Developer

Apr 2011 → Aug 2014

Gridnine Systems, Moscow, Russia

Prototyping conceptual wireframes and visual mockups for web applications (Photoshop, Illustrator).

Developing frontend part of a number of corporate web applications (Google Web Toolkit, JavaScript, Backbone.js and Require.js). Responsive layout with SASS and LESS. Programming Java servlets on the backend.

Recent Projects

Otixo. Web and iOS messenger focused on enhanced cloud file sharing capabilities.

React.JS, SASS, SemanticUI, Swift, UIKit

Lili. Social network for creating and sharing lists of things.

Angular.js, LESS, HTML, Swift, UIKit

<u>Bimmer Sticker Store</u>. Online e-commerce store featuring a collection of vinyl stickers for automobiles.

Bootstrap, SASS, EJS, Node.js, Snipcart

<u>SelimLab</u>. Research group website.

Bootstrap, SASS, EJS, Node.js

Maskd A homepage and identity for anonymous iOS messenger app.

Swift, HTML, LESS

Professional networks

- Check out my design portfolio on Dribbble.
- Look into my code on GitHub.
- Find my professional contacts on Linkedin.
- Skim through a list of my <u>publications on Google Scholar</u>.

Interests

Linux and open-source software. Fixing cars. Snowboarding and rollerblading.